jīnnián shì diān cáng gōnglù tōngchē 50 zhōunián
今年 是 滇 藏 公路 通车 50 周年
This year marks the 50th anniversary of the opening of the Yunnan-Tibet Highway.
zhōngxīng shè jìzhě xiānhòu cǎifǎng le 76 suì
中兴 社 记者 先后 采访 了 76 岁
Zhongxing News Agency reporters interviewed a 76-year-old
de diān cáng gōnglù zhùlù rén yáng jīnglíng
的 滇 藏 公路 助路 人 杨 精灵
Yang Jingling, the helper on the Yunnan-Tibet Highway
duōnián fènzhàn zài wéihù diāncáng gōnglù yīxiàn de
多年 奋战 在 维护 滇藏 公路 一线 的
After years of fighting on the front line of maintaining the Yunnan-Tibet highway
díqìng gōnglùjú zǔzhībù bùzhǎng gāoguì huá
迪庆 公路局 组织部 部长 高贵 华
Gao Guihua, Minister of Organization Department of Diqing Highway Bureau
yǐjí gēnsuí yéyé fùqīn de jiǎobù chéngwéi gōnglù
以及 跟随 爷爷 父亲 的 脚步 成为 公路
And follow in the footsteps of my grandfather and father to become a highwayman
rén de díqìng gōnglùjú jīxièhuà yǎnghù hé yìngjí
人 的 迪庆 公路局 机械化 养护 和 应急
People's Diqing Highway Bureau Mechanized Maintenance and Emergency Response
zhōngxīng zhígōng zhānglìjuān
中兴 职工 张力娟
Zhang Lijuan, employee of ZTE
cóng lǎozhōngqīng sāndài gōnglù rén de shìjiǎo láihuí
从 老中青 三代 公路 人 的 视角 来回
Reflecting from the perspectives of three generations of highway workers
wàng zhè tiáo tiān lù
望 这 条 天 路
Look at this heavenly road
qián bǎinián lái diān cáng liǎngdì bèi héngduànshānmài
前 百年 来 滇 藏 两地 被 横断山脉
For centuries, the regions of Yunnan and Tibet were separated by the Hengduan Mountains.
zǔgé 19 50 nián 8 yuè wèi wěngù
阻隔 19 50 年 8 月 为 稳固
Blocked since August 1950 for stability
xīnán biānfáng zēngjìn mínzútuánjié dǎtōng diāncáng
西南 边防 增进 民族团结 打通 滇藏
Southwest border defense enhances ethnic unity and opens up the Yunnan-Tibet route.
fāzhǎn tōngdào diāncáng gōnglù jiànshè lākāiwéimù
发展 通道 滇藏 公路 建设 拉开帷幕
The construction of the Yunnan-Tibet highway development corridor has begun.
xiūjiàn diāncáng gōnglù shí jiànshèzhě men kèfú gāohán
修建 滇藏 公路 时 建设者 们 克服 高寒
When building the Yunnan-Tibet highway, the builders overcame the high altitude cold.
quēyǎng shān gāo gǔshēng děng chóngchóngkùnnán xiānhòu
缺氧 山 高 鼓声 等 重重困难 先后
Oxygen deprivation, high mountains, drumbeats, and numerous difficulties come one after another.
yǒu 300 yúrén chángmián yú xuěyù gāoyuán
有 300 余人 长眠 于 雪域 高原
Over 300 people rest forever on the snowy plateau.
yǒuxiē tā shīgōng shíhòu jiù zài nàge
有些 它 施工 时候 就 在 那个
Some of them were already there during construction.
fǎshěng gōngshāng shìgù yǒu de tānfāng
法省 工商 事故 有 的 贪方
There is corruption in the industrial and commercial accidents of the province.
zásǐ le diào dào jiālǐ de gèzhǒng dōu
砸死 了 掉 到 家里 的 各种 都
Killed all kinds of things that fell into the house
yǒu tā gēn wǒ shuō guò wǒ jìde
有 他 跟 我 说 过 我 记得
He told me this, I remember.
yīnggāi zuì de shíhòu shì zài báimǎ xuěshān gōngjiān
应该 最 的 时候 是 在 白马 雪山 攻坚
The toughest time was probably during the assault on Baima Snow Mountain.
de shíhòu , dāngshí nàge dìfāng báimǎ
的 时候 , 当时 那个 地方 白马
At that time, that place, Baima
xuěshān zhōngnián jīxuě ,
雪山 中年 积雪 ,
Snow Mountain is covered in snow year-round,
ránhòu gāohán quēyǎng , tāmen
然后 高寒 缺氧 , 他们
with high altitude and lack of oxygen. They
jiù chī zài nàlǐ ,
就 吃 在 那里 ,
ate there,
zhù zài nàlǐ chī gānliáng ,
住 在 那里 吃 干粮 ,
lived there, ate dry rations,
ránhòu bǎ xuěhuàkāi le héshuǐ ,
然后 把 雪化开 了 河水 ,
and melted snow for river water,
zhíjiē jiù fēicháng de jiānkǔ 。 dāngshí
直接 就 非常 的 艰苦 。 当时
it was extremely hard. At that time,
hǎibá 4 300 mǐ de xuěshān jiù yìngshēngshēng
海拔 4 300 米 的 雪山 就 硬生生
on the 4,300-meter-high snow mountain, they forcibly
dìbèi tāmen yòng shǒuchí gōngjù háiyǒu kào zhàyào
地被 他们 用 手持 工具 还有 靠 炸药
used hand tools and explosives
zhà ránhòu zhà chū le yígè yākǒu tōngdào lái
炸 然后 炸 出 了 一个 压口 通道 来
to blast out a passage through a pass.
tā gēn wǒ jiǎng guò jiùshì tā de
他 跟 我 讲 过 就是 他 的
He told me that some of his
gōngyǒu yǒudeshì
工友 有的是
fellow workers were
bèi fēishí zásǐ de yǒudeshì zhuìyá
被 飞石 砸死 的 有的是 坠崖
killed by flying rocks, some fell off cliffs,
ránhòu háiyǒu de jiù dòngsǐ le diān zàn
然后 还有 的 就 冻死 了 滇 赞
and some froze to death. The Yunnan-Tibet
gōnglù nánqǐ yúnnán dàlǐ xiàguān xiánjiē diānmiǎngōnglù
公路 南起 云南 大理 下关 衔接 滇缅公路
Highway starts from Xiaguan, Dali, Yunnan, connecting to the Yunnan-Burma Highway,
běidǐ xīzàng mángkāng yǔ chuāncánggōnglù xiānglián
北底 西藏 盲康 与 川藏公路 相连
ends at Markam, Tibet, linking to the Sichuan-Tibet Highway.
7 15 gōnglǐ yánxiàn chuànglián dàlǐ
7 15 公里 沿线 创连 大理
715 kilometers long, it passes through Dali
、 lìjiāng 、
、 丽江 、
, Lijiang,
díqìngjí xīzàng mángkāng děng duō dì zhè tiáo
狄庆及 西藏 盲康 等 多 地 这 条
This road in Diqing, Tibet, and other places like Mangkang
tiān lù yào fānyuè báimǎ xuěshān 、
天 路 要 翻越 白马 雪山 、
must cross the Baima Snow Mountain,
hónglāshān děng xiǎnāi kuàyuè jīnshājiāng yǔ nán
红拉山 等 险埃 跨越 金沙江 与 南
the Hongla Mountains, and other dangerous passes, spanning the Jinsha River and the
cānjiāng bànshù lùduàn qiàn zài qiàobì zhīshàng
参江 半数 路段 嵌 在 峭壁 之上
Shencan River, with half of the road carved into cliffs.
xiūjiàn diāncáng gōnglù shí jīhū méiyǒu dàxíng jīxiè
修建 滇藏 公路 时 几乎 没有 大型 机械
When building the Yunnan-Tibet Highway, there were almost no large machines.
chútou jiāolúnchē shì zhǔyào
锄头 交轮车 是 主要
Hoe and wheelbarrow were the main
gōngjù měitiān nǐ měigè rén tǔfāng bìxū wánchéng
工具 每天 你 每个 人 土方 必须 完成
tools. Each person had to complete a daily quota of earthwork.
bāfāng wǒmen yòngjiāolúnchē tuīshì 12
八方 我们 用交轮车 推是 12
Eight cubic meters—we used wheelbarrows to push 12
chētǔ cái gòu yīfāng yītiān
车土 才 够 一方 一天
loads of earth to make one cubic meter. One day,
nǐ tuītǔ jiù bìxū yào tuī dào 90
你 推土 就 必须 要 推 到 90
you had to push over 90
duōchē dāngshí xīnlǐ dōu shì yígè xìnniàn
多车 当时 心里 都 是 一个 信念
loads. At that time, everyone had one belief:
gòngchǎnzhǔyì shèhuì yígè wèi guójiā
共产主义 社会 一个 为 国家
a communist society, working for the country.
gànhuó jiù méiyǒu sīxīnzániàn 23 nián de
干活 就 没有 私心杂念 23 年 的
We worked without selfish thoughts. After 23 years of
jiānkǔ fènzhàn diāncáng gōnglù zhǔxiàn 19 73 nián
艰苦 奋战 滇藏 公路 主线 19 73 年
hard struggle, the main line of the Yunnan-Tibet Highway was completed in November 1973,
11 yuè shíxiàn quánxiànguàntōng chèdǐ dǎpò diāncáng
11 月 实现 全线贯通 彻底 打破 滇藏
fully opening up, completely breaking the
biānjiāng jiāotōng bìsè luòhòu de fāzhǎn kùnjú
边疆 交通 闭塞 落后 的 发展 困局
development deadlock of border traffic isolation and backwardness.
19 76 nián 7 yuè 6 rì zhōngguó
19 76 年 7 月 6 日 中国
On July 6, 1976, Chinese
méitǐ fābù diāncáng gōnglù shènglì jiànchéng zhèngshì tōngchē
媒体 发布 滇藏 公路 胜利 建成 正式 通车
media announced the successful completion and official opening of the Yunnan-Tibet Highway
de xiāoxī
的 消息
to traffic.
zài zhùrù hùlù de guòchéng zhōng dāngdì mínzhòng
在 注入 户路 的 过程 中 当地 民众
During the process of building the road, local people
yě wèi gōnglù rénmen sòngshàng zuìnuǎnxīn de sūyóuchá
也 为 公路 人们 送上 最暖心 的 酥油茶
They also offer the warmest butter tea to the people on the road.
suānnǎi děng shíwù
酸奶 等 食物
And foods like yogurt.
yīdào nàge dìfāng lǎobǎixìng shì fēicháng huānyíng de
一到 那个 地方 老百姓 是 非常 欢迎 的
Once we arrived, the locals were very welcoming.
zàngzú yígè tèdiǎn tā dōu xǐhuān dǎ sūyóuchá
藏族 一个 特点 他 都 喜欢 打 酥油茶
One characteristic of Tibetans is that they all like to make butter tea.
qǐng nǐ hē
请 你 喝
They invite you to drink it.
rúguǒ nǐ dào zàngzú lǎobǎixìng jiālǐ tā jiù huì
如果 你 到 藏族 老百姓 家里 他 就 会
If you go to a Tibetan family's home, they will
fēicháng rèqíng dì gěi nǐ dǎshùyǔ chá hē
非常 热情 地 给 你 打树语 茶 喝
Very warmly make and serve you butter tea.
dāngshí nàzhǒng zài xuěcài dǐngshàng xiūlù zuì gǎnrén
当时 那种 在 雪菜 顶上 修路 最 感人
What was most touching back then, while building roads on the snowy plateau,
de shì zàngzú lǎo āmā gēn wǒmen shuō
的 是 藏族 老 阿妈 跟 我们 说
Was that Tibetan elder mothers would say to us,
háizi men hǎohǎo dìxiū bāng wǒmen yě xiū
孩子 们 好好 地修 帮 我们 也 修
"Children, build the road well, help us build it too."
yīxià jiù gěi wǒmen sònglái shùyóunǎi
一下 就 给 我们 送来 树油奶
Then they would bring us butter and milk.
50 nián hòu de jīntiān xīrì xiǎnjùn qíqū
50 年 后 的 今天 昔日 险峻 崎岖
Today, 50 years later, the once perilous and rugged
de jìnzhàn tiānxiǎn yǐdié biànwèi liánjiē diāncáng liǎngdì
的 近战 天险 以谍 变为 连接 滇藏 两地
mountain pass has transformed into a vital transportation artery linking Yunnan and Tibet.
de zhòngyào jiāotōng dòngmài
的 重要 交通 动脉
suízhe jiāotōng jīchǔshèshī chíxù wánshàn dīzàn gōnglù
随着 交通 基础设施 持续 完善 滴赞 公路
With continuous improvements in transportation infrastructure, the Dizan Highway
tōngxíng tiáojiàn dàfú tíshēng lǚyóu wùliú děng yánxiàn
通行 条件 大幅 提升 旅游 物流 等 沿线
has seen a significant upgrade in travel conditions. Along the route, tourism, logistics, and other
chǎnyè fāzhǎn rìyì fánróng jiànzhèng zhe xuěyù gāoyuán
产业 发展 日益 繁荣 见证 着 雪域 高原
industries are thriving, witnessing the changes of the snowy plateau.
de shídài biànqiān yǐqián dehuà zhēnde hěnnán
的 时代 变迁 以前 的话 真的 很难
In the past, it was really hard,
hěn nányào chī shàng yīkǒu xīnxiān de shūcài
很 难要 吃 上 一口 新鲜 的 蔬菜
very hard to get fresh vegetables
huòzhě shūguǒ zhèxiē nàlù xiūtōng le yǐhòu ne
或者 蔬果 这些 那路 修通 了 以后 呢
or fruits. After the road was built,
wàimiàn de wùzī kěyǐ jìnlái tíxǐng běndì de
外面 的 物资 可以 进来 提醒 本地 的
Outside supplies can come in, reminding locals
yīxiē tèchǎn sōngrōng a chóngcǎo a yàocái zhèxiē
一些 特产 松茸 啊 虫草 啊 药材 这些
Some specialties like matsutake, caterpillar fungus, and medicinal herbs
dōu kěyǐ yùnchūqù jiāotōng biànjié yǐhòu tā jīhuó
都 可以 运出去 交通 便捷 以后 它 激活
can all be shipped out. With convenient transportation, it has activated
le wénlǚ chǎnyè de fāzhǎn xiànzài wǒmen kěyǐ
了 文旅 产业 的 发展 现在 我们 可以
the development of cultural tourism. Now we can
kàndào G 21 4 xiàn de yánxiàn yǒu
看到 G 21 4 县 的 沿线 有
see along the G214 county line there are
hěnduō de mínsù jiǔdiàn cānyǐn duì
很多 的 民宿 酒店 餐饮 对
many homestays, hotels, and restaurants, which
yánxiàn de bǎixìng zēngshōu háishì tèbié yǒulì de
沿线 的 百姓 增收 还是 特别 有利 的
are particularly beneficial for increasing the income of local residents along the route.